What are you up to, Diti?
Master.
I wonder why,
but I've just been fatally wounded
by the lusty arrows of Kamadeva.
Were you so consumed by lust
that you couldn't stop
yourself from committing
a grave offense of disturbing a sage
during his evening prayers?
Master.
My father, Daksh,
gave his 13 daughters,
including me, in marriage to you.
You've blessed
all my sisters with children
and, in doing so,
completed their lives.
I am the only unfortunate one
who still remains childless.
Master, why this bias against me?
I desire to have a son.
Is something wrong
with my desire?
No, but what's wrong
is the time of the evening,
because at this hour,
ghosts, evil spirits, and demons,
along with their master, Lord Shiva,
roam the skies.
According to the scriptures,
if a woman has physical union
with her husband at
this hour of the evening,
there is every possibility
of a demonic soul
taking refuge in her womb.
That is why…
Diti.
I shall definitely fulfill your desire.
Please wait for some time.
If I could wait,
I would have never disturbed you
during your evening prayers
in the first place.
Obstinate woman!
Master, is there something wrong?
You look perturbed.
You foolish woman!
I had warned you
that the time was inauspicious
to conceive a child.
But you didn't heed my advice.
Now suffer!
Suffer?
What does that mean?
You rejected my advice
and thus disobeyed the directives
of the holy scriptures.
As a result,
two extremely demonic entities
have entered your womb.
You wanted a son, right?
Alas!
Now you will be the mother
of two ferocious demons!
Demons of such caliber
were neither born before
nor will they ever take birth again.
They will have only two objectives.
O Lord Mahadeva!
-To hate the divine…
-How could this happen?
…and to terrorize the devotees.
-They will unleash unparalleled violence…
-No!
…throughout the three worlds.
And when their atrocities
reach their pinnacle…
No, master!
…they will be slain by none other than
Lord Vishnu himself!
Such a grave misfortune!
O Lord Mahadeva!
I was blinded by lust,
so I could not differentiate
between right and wrong.
Kindly do not give me such
a harsh punishment for it.
Please forgive me, Lord Mahadeva!
Please forgive me.
No one escapes
the consequences of their actions.
Guru of the demonic clan, Shukracharya,
had been waiting for this day.
Please come inside quickly!
He was waiting for the warriors
who could defeat his archenemy,
and force the gods
to surrender before him.
He taught the twin brothers
about the dark arts
and the use of weapons of dark forces
that made them very powerful.
Soon, both brothers
mastered the dark arts
and gained supernatural powers.
Brother!
Unleashing their limitless powers,
they wreaked havoc
in the netherworld
and terrorized everyone.
To oppose them was
akin to inviting death.
The demon guru could bring
the dead back to life
a power that sustained
the demon race.
It was the beginning of a revolution,
and it was imperative to learn
more about the archenemy.
There is only one enemy of demons!
Vishnu!
The world was on the brink
of an inevitable upheaval,
and yet life was
flourishing somewhere else.
Here, everyone was filled with joy.
They lived in harmony with nature
and worshipped it too.
They understood the essence of
cows, wind, nature, and the divine.
And through yoga,
-they'd use them in his life effectively.
-Mother!
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
To please the gods,
the kings performed yajna and rituals.
Pleased with the purification
by the priests and yajna,
the gods themselves would appear
and deliver offerings to
the Supreme Lord Vishnu,
who, in turn, would bless
everyone with his mercy.
But they were unaware of the power
of these two demon brothers.
Save me!
Let go of me!
Mother!
What sort of shameless people are they?
They worship trees,
plants, cows, and cow dung!
And is he the king?
Weaklings!
These creatures shall die…
Hiranyaksha!
If you want to rule the three worlds,
then leave these creatures.
We must now wage war
upon their souls!
There is a long way to go, my brother!
We will take away
everything they have!
Everything!
Everything has been destroyed!
Our society.
Our people.
All our dreams.
Because you want everything!
O Lord!
Where are you?
Brother.
-We've robbed everything they had!
-It's impossible!
No matter what you do,
finish everything, rob us as much
as you want, or destroy our civilization!
You will never be able to
take one thing away from us.
Our faith in Lord Vishnu!
Hiranyakashyap, remember.
You may want to rule over everyone,
but from this moment on,
you will be heading
towards your destruction.
And there will come a day
when your arrogance will
lead you to your downfall,
and then you will
invite your own death.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
O Lord!
Vishnu.
What is so great about Vishnu?
The great thing about Vishnu is
that he is cunning and deceptive
who always wants
to humiliate the demons
by favoring the gods.
Truth be told, right now,
he is hiding, and he's fearful.
That coward, hypocrite!
Through deceit, he has enchanted
the entire world to such an extent
that these fools
see Vishnu in every living being.
They think Vishnu is in everything!
Vishnu also believes
that everything revolves around him,
and the rest of us are insignificant!
So this insignificant Hiranyaksha
shall now rob everything, Brother!
The destruction of every living being
will be done
by these insignificant hands.
Hiranyaksha.
No matter how much
destruction you cause,
that coward will continue
to hide in fear.
It seems Vishnu loves to hide, right?
I shall hide the entire earth.
Then he'll be forced to come out.
Vishnu will have to come out!
Not for earth,
but to find Goddess Earth!
Understood, Brother!
I need your blessings for this task.
The entire demon clan
shall eagerly await your return.
Dear brother, don't lose your way
while you chase Vishnu.
Now get ready to kill
Vishnu with your bare hands.
Hiranyakashipu,
the great demon, is my brother.
So to kill Vishnu,
all I need are these pitiful hands
and a single slap.
After slaying Vishnu,
I will drink his blood in your honor.
Please command me.
May you be victorious!
Bhume Bhumi pa saravsve
Bhumi pala prayane
Bhumi pa ahankara rupe
Bhumi devi cha Bhumi de
Bhumi dehi cha Bhumi de
Om Vasundharaya vidmahe
Bhutadhatraya dhimahi
Tanno Bhumih prachodayat
O Lord!
Let go of me!
Leave me!
Wicked demon,
my lord will destroy you!
Leave me!
O Lord, protect me!
O Grandsire!
Please enlighten us
about this mystery.
No demon has ever abused his powers
to such a barbaric extent.
So much violence
against Goddess Earth!
Feels like a nightmare!
O Creator of the universe!
Kindly find a way
to rescue Goddess Earth
from the depths of
the Causal Ocean at the earliest.
If there is anyone who can save
Goddess Earth from this grave crisis,
it's only Lord Vishnu.
O Lord,
kindly protect Goddess Earth.
Look over there.
What is this?
Incredible!
Who is this strange being?
Unbelievable!
He just emerged from my nostrils.
Om Varahaya namah
Om!
Dhanur-dharaya vidmahe
Vakra-damstraya dhimahi
Tanno Varahah prachodayat
O Lord.
Lord, is that you?
Finally, you came to my rescue!
How dare you take Goddess Earth
away in my presence?
Stop right there, boar!
You wild boar!
I feel disgusted by your mere sight!
This is the Varaha avatar
of Lord Vishnu.
Hail the Lord!
Hail Lord Varaha.
Om Varahaya namah
Get ready to die, Vishnu.
You…
O Lord Narayana!
Lord Brahma!
Impossible!
O Lord Narayana,
for you, slaying this demon
is as simple
as squashing an ant.
Then why are you
toying with this demon?
Kindly slay him at the earliest
and rid us of our fear.
Congratulations!
You have done us a great favor
by slaying this wicked demon.
We express our gratitude to you.
O Lord,
ordinarily, a boar is considered
to be an abominable creature.
However, even in this form,
your body is resplendent,
divine,
and transcendental.
Anyone who meditates upon
this wonderful form of yours,
or listens to this wonderful tale
of yours with full faith
will certainly invite
auspiciousness into their lives.
All hail Lord Varaha!
Son!
Do not grieve
the martyrdom of your son.
Rather, let your chest swell in pride.
Because warriors like him
don't take birth very often.
And martyrdom is an honor in itself.
After slaying Vishnu,
I shall drink his blood
in your honor, brother!
Don't lose your way
while you chase Vishnu.
Instigated by gods,
Vishnu has been very unjust to us.
He has deceived us.
He has deceived us!
Upon this funeral pyre
is not just my brother who burns,
but rather the very future
of our demon race!
Our future is in danger.
If we do not retaliate,
we will be subject
to deceit upon deceit.
Do you want to pass
on such a grim legacy
to our future generations?
No!
Now is the time for revenge!
Butcher all those
who are devoted to Vishnu.
Let's wreak havoc!
You worship Vishnu!
Within no time,
Hiranyakashyap's atrocities
wreaked havoc upon
every Vishnu devotee.
Fearful, the gods hid themselves
and started planning a war.
But Lord Indra, the king of gods,
was worried about something else.
He was worried about
the future heir
of the demon clan.
Sire.
I have caused widespread bloodshed
to avenge Hiranyaksha's death.
Despite this, I'm not at peace.
And that is because
the slayer of my brother still lives!
You are undoubtedly very powerful.
But you are no match for Vishnu.
If you really want to fight him,
you have to become as powerful as he is.
How do I accomplish this?
Start worshipping Lord Brahma.
You shall be granted a boon.
Yes, master.
An expectant mother needs her
husband by her side.
Kindly do not leave me
at this stage.
Revenge, penance.
Kindly abandon such thoughts.
Although the lion is
the king of the jungle,
to hunt a deer, he must wake up
from his slumber.
How do I let go
of these thoughts, Kayadhu?
How?
Not at all!
If becoming God is what it takes
to slay Lord Vishnu,
then I, Hiranyakashyap,
will move heaven and earth,
but I shall surely become God!
The path of righteousness
is defined by truth and justice,
and this path is difficult.
Many falter while walking this path.
Be it demons
or even gods.
Envy and wrath
may divert us
from the path of righteousness.
But destiny can be so strange
that a teacher always appears
at the right time
as a guiding light.
Like Sage Narada, who revealed
the path of righteousness to Lord Indra
and guided him on that path.
Hence, everything depends on
who you choose as a guide
and what his true intent is.
Kayadhu, it's very important
for an expectant woman
to devote herself
completely to Lord Vishnu
and listen to his tales.
This has a positive impact on
the child growing in her womb.
Om, salutations to Lord Brahma.
Lord Vishnu, as a supreme soul,
resides in the heart of everyone.
The Lord is the witness to all,
and the easiest way
to attain his devotion is…
Om, salutations to Lord Brahma.
…to chant his name
with utmost devotion.
Om, salutations to Lord Brahma.
So let us all say wholeheartedly,
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Om, salutations to Lord Brahma.
The power of penance
of this demon
will burn down the entire universe.
Arise,
oh, son of Sage Kashyap,
Hiranyakashipu.
O Creator of the universe.
O progenitor grandsire,
you neither have
a beginning nor an end.
You are the upholder of the cosmos.
The entire creation,
along with all its species
rest within you.
I, Hiranyakashyap, bow down
to the supreme creator.
I am pleased with your penance.
Tell me, what boon do you seek?
Everything!
O Lord Brahma,
kindly grant me a boon,
let death never touch me
by any creature you've made,
be it God, a human, or any beast.
Let my death come
neither by day nor by night.
May I not die
inside the house, nor outside it.
May I not be slain by any weapon,
neither by the living nor the non-living.
Moreover,
grant me all the powers
that can be attained through
the practice of mystic yoga.
May all fame and opulence
of the three worlds be mine.
May I henceforth be the undisputed
master of all living entities.
Grant me unlimited powers
so that I become the most powerful man
in this entire universe.
O Lord Brahma!
Make me the most powerful man!
Such a boon has never been
bestowed upon anyone till now.
However, it is also true
that the kind of severe penance
that you have performed
has never been attempted in the past,
nor would it be attempted in the future.
So be it!
I have become immortal!
Finally, I have become God!
Let everyone say and everyone chant
that Hiranyakashipu is God!
That Hiranyakashipu is God!
Get ready, Indra!
Hiranyakashipu.
I extend my hand in friendship.
The hands that have
dared to abduct my wife
should be
chopped off mercilessly.
Don't you forget
that you are my lowly servant,
and servants cannot be friends.
Now remember,
henceforth, I am the King of Heaven!
The wheels of time are spinning!
A moment ago,
Indra was the King of Heaven,
but the very next moment,
he became a menial servant!
Now, all of you,
listen to me carefully.
Continue to discharge
our duties diligently,
but only for me
and in accordance with my will alone.
Henceforth, I am your only God.
Only my idols shall preside
in all the temples.
All the sacrificial offerings
shall be mine alone.
Scriptures for you will be only
those which extol my glories,
and you shall
chant only one mantra.
Let everyone say
and everyone chant
that Hiranyakashipu is God!
Say it!
Vishnu, take a look!
I will destroy
your devotees one by one,
and soon my son will be
wreaking havoc on them.
Now that will force you to come out!
When darkness takes over,
there appears a ray of the divine.
Destiny worked its wonder,
and right in the heart
of the dark empire
flickered a flame of righteousness.
His name was…
Prahlad.
Mother.
You dwell in my heart
My life, my pride
Before sorrows reach you
I would embrace death
As bright as the sun
As serene as the moon
You're the light of my life
You're my world
-May you never falter
-Greetings.
May you reach for the stars
May you fill every heart with love
May everyone love you
Many trials and tests await you
Do not fear
Time will ease all your pains
Just keep smiling
Let our hearts' garden bloom
With your divine light
Alone by your divine light
Spread kindness and righteousness
Make everything bright
This is my wish for you
I pray for your victory
The world will recall
This is my prayer
You dwell in my heart
My life, my pride
Before sorrows reach you
O Lord.
Look what I brought for you.
What is all this?
Vishnu?
Prince, your father
Hiranyakashyap is our God.
By worshipping Lord Vishnu,
you are going against your father.
If your father finds out,
it will be a disaster.
Vishnu will never meet you, Prince.
You are right.
I am a demon.
Perhaps I am not worthy
of meeting him.
But devotion is not
a matter of clan or caste.
It is a matter of the heart.
Prahlad.
Come to me, my son.
Greetings, Father!
To conquer the cosmos
and command the gods brings great joy,
but nothing compares
to the love of a son.
Prahlad, today you are sitting in my lap,
but in the future,
you will ascend the throne.
So I propose that we have
a small test to see the skills
and the wisdom of our future
little prince, what say?
Certainly, Father.
Alright, Prahlad.
Based on what you've
studied in the gurukul,
tell us what it takes to be a king?
Father,
a king is someone who delivers
justice without bias,
who treats his subjects
like his own children,
and stands with his people,
in both joy and grief.
A king not only
rules over the kingdom,
but also rules over
the hearts of his subjects.
Bravo! Brilliant!
Your words of wisdom
make my heart elated.
The future of the demon clan
is in safe hands
Don't stop, go on.
The prime duty of a king
is to inspire his subjects
to seek refuge with the supreme being,
motivate them to be devoted
to the supreme guardian, and all-powerful,
and he is none other
than Lord Vishnu!
Disillusioned by ignorance,
false pride, and false attachments,
every living being is drowning in
the great ocean of worldly existence.
But Lord Vishnu comes as a ship
that can save our souls,
then he can easily sail across
the ocean of ignorance…
That's it!
Enough of Vishnu's glorification!
You definitely speak
like a learned person.
Unfortunately, somebody
has poisoned your learning.
But you are not to be blamed.
Shand and Amark!
It appears that devotees of Vishnu
have infiltrated our gurukul in disguise
and are misleading my son.
Both of you have been
entrusted with a great responsibility.
Henceforth, be alert and ensure
that no devotees of Vishnu
can infiltrate the gurukul.
Or else…
A symbol of courage, the roar of power,
violence is the pride of demons.
The destruction of the weak
is the sole duty of the powerful.
Hiranyakashipu praises particularly
those who partake in violence.
Sire.
Yes, Prahlad?
Isn't it the duty of a powerful
individual to protect the weak?
Of course, otherwise,
how can the weak survive?
There's no place for the weak here!
And that's the only truth of life.
Svasty astu visvasya khalah prasidatam
Dhyayantu bhutani sivam mitho dhiya
Beautiful!
Prahlad, please also tell us
the meaning of this.
Manah ca bhadram bhajatad adhoksaje
Avesyatam no matih apy ahaituki
Wonderful.
-How is that even possible?
-Prahlad.
Are you doing it or…
-Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
-Who is Vasudeva?
What's the secret?
Vasudeva is Hari Narayana.
Who is Hari?
I am not able to understand anything.
Come, hear this story
Of the Divine's grace
Where happiness and hope find their place
All creatures depend on him
Big and small
He makes the world go around
What's devotion?
Is it all true or is it all myths?
Where will we find strength?
Where did you find yours?
Look closely, don't hide away
Let's uncover the truth today
You say the Divine is always near
But if we can't see him
Does he really exist?
Like the breeze we feel, but cannot see
Or the sunshine warming you and me
Isn't it so?
Like the breeze we feel, but cannot see
Or the sunshine warming you and me
Isn't it so?
That is how Divine is
The Divine is everywhere
In every moment, the ultimate truth
Everything else is an illusion
Fish need water to swim and play
Butterflies need flowers
To brighten their day
Leaves need branches to hold them tight
And rain needs clouds to bring delight
What does it mean, this divine bond?
Without it, everything seems so wrong
We're complete
When we're aligned with Divine
Let's chant together
With hearts entwined
Namah, om namah, namah Narayana
In every moment, the Divine is with me
In every soul, in every place
Lies the Divine's loving embrace
In every moment, the Divine is with me
In every soul, in every place
Lies the Divine's loving embrace
Keep us safe, O Madhava
We pray to you, our refuge
Never leave us, always be there
Keep us safe, O Madhava
We pray to you, our refuge
Never leave us, always be there
Namah, om namah, namah Narayana
Akhanda, what are you doing?
We are demons.
These petty games do not
bring glory to our gurukul.
But I don't understand
what I have done to rile you up.
Prahlad!
A prince should be powerful and radiant.
Not someone as compassionate
and empathic as you
who believes in
a superstition like Vishnu.
What's wrong with being
compassionate and empathic?
Also, devotion to Vishnu
is not a superstition.
They worship Vishnu!
They eat grass, flowers, and fruits!
My friend, what's
wrong with eating fruits?
Even his teeth are different from ours!
Such a shame
for the demon clan.
Despite being a prince,
you don't know how to conduct
a show of force.
How does taking the life of a powerless
creature become a show of force?
I won't die of hunger.
After all, we are all living beings
created by the same divine force.
Force! Whose?
Oh, yes!
The king of the coward,
the beloved of the weak.
The imaginary force of our dear prince.
Supreme Lord Vishnu?
The entire universe fears us.
You also must understand
the reason for this fear, my prince!
Violence is my duty,
and Hiranyakashyap is my God!
It is my privilege…
-No, my friend--
-…to fulfill this duty.
Dinna!
How is he still standing on his feet?
He is surely strong.
You've endured this pain to save me?
It is the duty of the powerful
to protect the weak!
The duty of a prince
is to protect his people.
You are compassionate,
but not weak.
Prince Prahlad!
All hail Prince Prahlad!
Love and devotion are the only languages
understood by every being
in this entire universe.
However, to understand love and devotion,
we must surrender completely.
One name is the solution
to all of life's troubles.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
And our boat will sail
on the path of love and devotion,
which is the path of righteousness.
It's very beautiful.
Only if it were all true.
What's the matter, Baksia?
Is there anything wrong? Please tell us.
The story of Vishnu may sound
beautiful in your imagination,
but in reality…
In reality? What do you mean?
It's really dark in here!
We're at a great height.
You deserve this, Vishnu devotees!
Open your eyes and take a look.
Sooner or later,
we will be walking the same path.
Let everyone say
and everyone chant…
Lord Vishnu is our God.
You chant Vishnu's name.
You chant our enemy's name.
You traitor!
A powerful individual imposes
violence upon the weak.
He destroys them!
If you want to save yourself
from the anguish of fire,
then learn this principle.
This is how the world works
because violence is inevitable
Mother, father.
Sacrificing our loved ones
to this raging inferno
is now our ultimate fate.
This is not true!
-Yes, all these people are murderers.
-Murderers?
You think all those children
are murderers?
There's only one solution.
Forsake your God
and embrace the teachings of the gurukul,
my prince!
Oh my dear Lord!
How do I liberate all these devotees?
Show me a way.
Prahlad!
What's the matter?
Just as Prahlad explained
to us about Lord Vishnu,
he can also convince our king.
If our king ends his conflict with
Lord Vishnu, we'll all be saved.
From today onward, your life will
be entangled
in only suffering and thorns.
Because even Vishnu
wishes the same.
He never tried to save
his devotees and other gods.
So why would he come for
a five-year-old demon boy?
You will be alone!
Devotee Prahlad!
I'll continue to chant
the glory of Lord Vishnu
until everyone is liberated!
I'll only need to chant one name
and surrender wholeheartedly.
Liberation is through that one name alone.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Prahlad.
I hope you will not disappoint me
like you did the last time.
So, repeat whatever you've
learned from your teachers.
My teachers have taught me
that Lord Vishnu happens
to be our greatest enemy.
Excellent, Prahlad! Excellent!
So, you've finally gotten
Vishnu out of your head!
Your education has
finally borne fruit, son.
Shand.
Amark.
I reward you both with
a hundred gold coins each.
What's the need for
such largesse, Your Majesty?
We didn't do this to earn a reward.
We're saved from being roasted alive!
By declaring Vishnu to be your enemy,
you have pleased me greatly, son.
Forgive me, Father.
You asked me to repeat
the teachings of my teachers,
so I told you.
But I have not accepted
their teachings.
I definitely do not consider
Lord Vishnu to be my enemy.
Father, if at all you want to
consider somebody as an enemy,
please look within your heart for
lust, anger, greed, attachment, pride,
and envy, and consider them as enemies.
It is easier still to
conquer the universe,
but to conquer
these six deadly enemies
is far more difficult.
Quiet!
Even great gods tremble
to speak in my presence.
But this little boy dares to preach to me!
Kindly do not be angry, Father.
I plead with you
to kindly abandon your animosity
toward Lord Vishnu
and seek his refuge.
Seek refuge with cowardly Vishnu?
I'm Hiranyakashyap! All-powerful
and the conqueror of the three worlds!
No one can slay Hiranyakashipu!
How could you sing praises of someone
who has murdered
your uncle, Hiranyaksha?
Don't you have any sense
of loyalty towards your uncle?
My uncle was guilty of committing a sin
of submerging Earth into
the depths of the Causal Ocean.
Lord Varaha was perfectly
justified in slaying him.
Traitor!
You are akin to a deceitful serpent
that wouldn't hesitate
to bite your loved ones.
Shand, Amark! Both of you
have failed in your duties.
I punish both of you with
a hundred whiplashes each.
Have mercy, Your Majesty.
Have mercy upon us.
We beg you
not to punish us so harshly.
We are not at fault, Your Majesty.
We gave it our all,
but your son Prahlad is so stubborn
that he simply doesn't listen to us.
Worse, he is instigating other children
in the gurukul to rebel against you.
Your Majesty, your son
Prahlad is very cunning by nature.
What could we have done differently?
Hiranyakashipu.
Do you understand
Vishnu's shrewd game now?
Using your son like a battle-axe,
he desires to fell
the gigantic tree of the demon race!
You're right, Sire!
But before Vishnu succeeds
in his nefarious designs,
I'll sentence Prahlad
-to death!
-No!
No, Master!
What grave sin are you about to commit?
History has never witnessed
a father pronouncing
the death sentence
to his son.
Don't think that I am happy
making this decision!
But please know
that besides being a father,
I am also the guardian
of the demon clan.
Protection of my clan
is my responsibility!
If I spare Prahlad today,
sooner or later, he will cause
the destruction of the entire demon race.
Prahlad is only a five-year-old boy.
He's your son!
In our demonic clan,
there can be no place
for sentiments that weaken
one's heart, Kayadhu.
-Please spare him!
-Soldiers!
Use your weapons
and chop Prahlad into pieces!
No!
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Why did you stop?
Demons, attack!
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Om!
Narayanaya Vidmahe
Vasudevaya Dhimahi
Tanno
Vishnuh
Prachodayat
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Wh-- What is this phenomenon, Sire?
It is not a phenomenon,
but rather an open challenge by Vishnu.
You want to kill your son,
whereas he wants to protect his devotee.
It is no longer just a simple dispute
between a father and a son.
Now it's about who is superior.
Prahlad is merely a puppet
in the hands of two great powers.
If this is about superiority,
who between us is the greatest,
then I, Hiranyakashipu,
can go to any lengths to prove
my superiority over Vishnu.
Even if it means sacrificing
my own son in the process.
Soldiers!
I command that Prahlad
should be crushed publicly
under the feet of mad elephants.
Take him away!
Master!
I assure you
that I will persuade Prahlad
and turn him into an obedient child.
Kindly give me an opportunity.
Kayadhu.
On the one hand,
there is your husband's prestige
and on the other, your son's life.
An ideal wife will always choose her
husband's prestige over her son's life.
At stake here is not your prestige!
But your ego!
Kayadhu!
Isn't he our king's son?
No.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Let everyone say
and everyone chant…
Hiranyakashyap is our God.
Prahlad, there's still time.
Stop being so obsessed with Vishnu.
You won't be punished.
These elephants are certainly mad,
but your madness has no parallel.
Yes. I am mad!
Madly devoted to Lord Vishnu.
But what to do? My devotion
to him borders on intoxication!
It is your misfortune
that you couldn't experience
this divine joy.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
…Lord Vasudeva.
Certainly, some divine power
is protecting this child.
O Lord.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Oh, dear!
I'm feeling giddy
just by looking down.
Wow.
Exquisite beauty!
And why not?
After all, Lord Narayana is the artist.
You naive boy.
We haven't brought
you here for sightseeing
We're here to kill you by
pushing you down the cliff.
Oh! But please know
that you cannot kill me.
So you really think
that you won't die
if you're thrown from the cliff?
It is the body that dies,
not the soul.
I am more than this mortal body.
Most certainly, my body
will be destroyed
if I am thrown down this cliff.
But I shall be reborn later
into another family
or in another form
with a new body.
My soul shall always exist
irrespective of whether
my body exists or not.
Do you still believe
that you can kill me?
After hearing his words of wisdom,
I am now perplexed.
If it is not possible to
kill him in the real sense,
then why should
we push him off the cliff?
No.
You must push me down,
because obeying your
King's order is your duty.
Despite such atrocities
inflicted upon you by your father,
you still don't hate him?
Fathers are worthy of respect.
Are you not afraid at all?
How can there be darkness
Where the sun shines fully bright?
Once you fall at the Lord's feet
How can you feel any fright then?
The one who has protected me so far
shall protect me in the future too.
What if he doesn't come
to your rescue this time?
So what if he doesn't?
He can treat me the way he wants.
Because under all circumstances,
he's my lord and master.
Kindly don't feel sad for me.
Please carry out the task
you've been sent for.
Child, you truly are an enigma.
After hearing such profound
realizations from you,
we now tremble to commit this sin.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Come, my friend.
Let's get Prahlad's dead body.
Hey!
-What's this?
-Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
O Lord Narayana!
This miracle is completely your doing!
By protecting your devotee,
you have proven for
the rest of eternity
that you are the well-wisher
of your devotees.
Today, you have conquered
the hearts of despicable fools!
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Seething with anger,
Hiranyakashyap
tried to kill Prahlad many times
But Lord Vishnu kept
protecting him from every attack.
The light of his devotion
was spreading far and wide.
He very well knew that
his subjects were getting influenced
after witnessing the divine power
of Lord Vishnu
and would soon turn against him.
Now he was left with only one choice.
Holika.
Under the guardianship
of Guru Shukracharya,
Hiranyaksha and I had
acquired various mystic powers.
At the same time, you, too, were
blessed with quite a unique power.
That you could burn to
ashes anybody you desire,
but at the same time,
you will remain immune to fire.
I want you to use this boon
against Prahlad.
Let me remind you,
the boon was granted
to me on the condition
that I would use it
only for my self-defense
and that I'd never abuse it.
Holika.
Prahlad's heart beats for our enemy.
He's a devotee of Vishnu!
If we spare his life,
he'll certainly destroy
our demon clan.
By killing Prahlad, you shall
not only be protecting our clan,
but also protecting yourself.
Hence, this is a noble use of your boon.
Not a misuse!
Holika.
I consider you to be my sister.
I ask you,
in this hour of need,
to stand by me.
For sure, Brother!
Actually, you're right.
Prahlad has to die!
By engaging me in such
a worthy cause for our clan,
you've greatly honored me, Brother.
When every part of Prahlad's
fragile body is consumed by fire,
when his shriek echoes in my ears,
I shall truly feel that my life
has been indeed worthy!
But why do you need
Holika for such a simple task?
Just cast Prahlad into the fire,
and he'll simply burn to death.
Fire alone can do Prahlad no harm.
Because that illusory Vishnu is
always by his side to protect him!
I want you to sit upon a burning pyre
and hold Prahlad close
so that under no
circumstance can he escape.
Prahlad, my dear son.
Do not worry.
Your aunt is now here for you!
In her lap, you shall
sleep ever so peacefully!
By the way,
I have invited a priest
tonight who will carry out
your final rites even
before we can recover your
ashes from the pyre!
Mother.
Has anyone passed away?
For whom is this pyre prepared?
Please tell me.
Prahlad!
My child!
Prahlad,
I'll sit on this pyre with you in my lap,
and then I am going to
burn you to ashes.
This pyre is being built for you, child!
Both of you should be ashamed.
If you can't stop a cruel injustice
against a helpless child,
the least you can do
is not mock him.
Mother, please don't weep.
Seeing you cry fills me with sadness.
Oh, Prahlad!
Oh! Looks like Prahlad
is finally scared for his life
after looking at this imposing pyre.
I am not worried for myself.
It is you I am worried
about, my dear aunt.
I'm getting punished, not you.
I plead with you not to enter
the pyre with me,
else you will be burnt to ashes.
We shall find out soon enough
who will burn
and who will walk out alive!
Father,
kindly dissuade her,
or else you will repent.
Alright.
If you cease your devotion
towards Vishnu, I shall certainly
stop her from entering the pyre
and forgive you as well.
Forget about him, Prahlad.
-Forget about Vishnu!
-Mother.
How can you give me such ill advice,
despite being my mother?
Father.
Lord Vishnu draws me in
just as a magnet draws iron filings.
I have absolutely no
control over this attraction.
You stubborn fool!
You deserve to die!
Holika, take him up the pyre!
Let's go, Prahlad!
Mother…
To witness my own child burning alive
I know the blaze within a mother's heart
burns more violently
than any pyre ever could.
If not for your son,
at least for the sake of your wife,
please spare Prahlad!
I shall also enter the pyre.
I shall enter the pyre.
Take her away to the palace.
Goodbye, Prahlad.
Aunt.
Come on.
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
It's burning.
I can't move!
Brother!
Save me, Brother!
Brother, I'm burning!
Save me!
Holika!
Save me, Brother!
-I'm burning!
-Someone put out the fire.
Brother!
Quick!
Holika!
Do something, quick!
Get me out of this fire!
Brother!
Save me!
Do something!
Holika!
-Bring water! Quick!
-Save me!
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Wait, I'll do something.
Put out the fire! Quick!
Get the water!
Put out the fire!
Everyone, get together
and put out the fire.
Holika!
…Lord Vasudeva!
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Father,
-I had pleaded with you.
-Holika.
Not to send Aunt into the pyre,
or else you would have to repent.
Murderer of my sister!
Get out of my sight!
Take him away
and throw him into an ocean.
Holika!
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva.
Wake up, Prahlad.
I am the Lord
of the water bodies and the oceans.
I am Lord Varun.
While chanting Lord Narayana's name,
you had forgotten everything,
and you weren't even aware
that only a few moments ago,
you were drowning in this deep ocean.
A devotee like you
is born only once in millennia.
I bow down to you.
I feel fortunate to be
in your blessed presence.
But my eyes are desperate
to behold that gem
who rests majestically
in the Ocean of Milk
on the divine serpent Shesha,
and he is illuminating the entire
creation by his dazzling brilliance.
If you can show me a way
to attain that gem,
I shall be indebted to you for life.
Do you think that this
desire to meet is yours alone
and not his?
He is also pining to see you.
Just call out to him once!
May victory be yours!
Even the greatest of gods
cannot get a glimpse of him,
how can a lowly creature like me,
who was born into a family of demons,
dream of seeing that Supreme Lord?
This wish of mine is as childish as
a wish of an insignificant ant
who wishes to gulp down
the entire water of this ocean.
O Lord, what do I do?
For I have no one else but you.
When I was forsaken by
my own family and relatives,
it was you alone
who stood by me.
Just like a child feels fearful
after being separated
from his mother in a crowded place,
I also feel fearful
as I am separated from you
all alone in this vast world.
O Lord, please come and hold my hand.
I am not worthy enough
to see you in person.
Yet I desire to see you.
Kindly appear before me.
O Lord, kindly appear before me.
You cried out to me, and here I am!
What happened?
Won't you say something?
I am in the presence of God!
Not God.
Rather, I'm your servant!
For an exalted devotee like you,
I'm only a servant.
And I shall remain one.
For you have won me through
your unmotivated, selfless love!
O Lord, you are the supreme God!
Kindly do not embarrass me by
identifying yourself as my servant.
Tell me, Prahlad.
What can I do for you?
Now that I have attained you,
what else remains to be attained?
All my desires
have been fulfilled today.
I desire nothing from you.
And should you still insist upon
giving me something,
then oh, Lord,
I want you to bless me
with a flame of devotion
which will
forever burn bright
in my heart for you
and that I may never forget you,
even for a moment.
Prahlad,
I bless you
that henceforth you shall
perceive my presence
everywhere and in all things.
So be it!
I bow to the Supreme Lord Narayana!
I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva
Today, you've revealed yourself, my dear
Now, every moment, every direction
I find you near
I've lost all my senses
You are my only support
I desired you with all my heart
Finally, I found you
Diving in clouds, I soar
Flying over oceans, I explore
I can't hold back anymore
Hold me tight, evermore
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva
Govind Madhav, victory to you
Oh, beloved, I am yours, so true
Calling out to you, there's light
My life now is bright
With every step I take
I call out to you from my heart
Your name, I celebrate
Om, I bow to the Supreme Lord Vasudeva
You lowly, filthy traitor!
You have survived yet again!
Are you not ashamed to present
yourself before me again and again?
I swear I will punish that hypocritical,
cowardly Vishnu.
Father,
I request you
not to address our beloved,
all-compassionate father,
Lord Narayana with such demeaning words.
Well, well!
An insult to that beloved,
all-compassionate father hurts you!
But you brazenly heap insults
on your father,
and it does not bother you at all!
Is your affection reserved
solely for Vishnu and none for me?
It is not so, Father.
I love you with all my heart.
Really? Doesn't quite seem like it!
Our father-son relationship is
limited to just this one lifetime.
But the Lord…
He has been my father
in all the previous births.
He is my father in this lifetime
and shall remain so
in my future births as well.
Not just mine,
he is your father as well.
He is everyone's father!
You might regard him as your enemy,
but God loves his enemies
a million times more
than a mother can ever love her child!
The whole world bows down
to Hiranyakashyap!
Who needs the worthless,
hollow love of that pretender?
You are a stooge of
that Vishnu, aren't you?
So call out to him!
Perhaps that coward may face me
upon listening to your pleas.
Let today be the day that decides
who between us
is a jackal, and who is a lion!
We need to call out to someone
who is not present.
The one you want to call out
is omnipresent.
He is everywhere.
He is all-pervading.
He is present
in each living being
and non-living thing in this assembly.
Keep quiet, you silly boy.
You're talking rubbish.
Show me where he is?
I don't see him around here.
Prahlad!
Your Vishnu is omnipresent, right?
In that case, he must be
inside this pillar, right?
Without a doubt!
Then pray for your words
to be truthful, Prahlad!
Because if he is not
found inside this pillar,
then today I, Hiranyakashyap,
right here in this whole assembly,
will sever your head from your body!
Today, I challenge your Vishnu
to rescue you from my wrath.
Let us all find out
how far Vishnu can go
to protect his devotee.
Ugram Viram Maha-Vishnum
Jvalantam Sarvato Mukham
Nrsimham Bhisanam Bhadram
Mrtyur Mrtyum Namamy Aham
Om!
Hail Lord Narsimha!
He is Vishnu!
No one will touch him.
He's my prey.
Finally! There you are!
Since you have called for your death,
I have to come to finish you off.
You clumsy pretender!
You fight with your enemies
sometimes, as a boar
sometimes as a lion!
Don't you get bored with such antics?
Whatever be my form,
rest assured
that today you will die
a very horrific death!
Just like your brother, Hiranyaksha,
who died at my hands.
You should threaten
only if you have
the power to make it true.
All hail Lord Narsimha!
Now this fight is going to be exciting.
Then why wait?
Lift your weapon and attack me!
Surely!
Om, salutations to Lord Brahma.
Kill him!
I am the sun that lights up
the deepest darkness with fear.
I'm a storm that
destroys everything in its path
and fire that burns everything.
Gods are terrified
by just hearing my name!
I am the king of all directions,
and my power is supreme!
Heavens and earth
accept me as the ultimate!
Because I am the ultimate darkness!
Vanamali gadi
Sarngi sankhi cakri ca nandaki
Sriman Narayano Vishnur
Vasudevo bhiraksatu
Om! I offer salutations
To Lord Narayana!
Your time…
is up!
…Lord Vasudeva!
Death cannot touch me,
neither within the four walls
nor beyond them.
Neither upon the earth…
nor in the sky.
Not by any weapon,
either animate or inanimate
cannot kill me.
You have anything to say now, right?
Hiranyakashyap,
when will you understand?
I am the supreme father!
Lord Brahma is my creation.
I am the supreme creator.
I am God!
You fool!
Look at me!
I'm neither a man nor an animal.
I'm Narsihma!
Look at the setting sun.
It's neither day,
nor night.
Furthermore, you are
neither inside your house
nor outside your house.
Look, you're at the entrance.
Neither are you on the ground
nor in the sky.
You are on my lap!
And speaking of weapons,
look at my claws.
They are neither of the living,
nor of the dead!
Hail Lord Narayana!
We all should go and express
our gratitude to Lord Vishnu.
Do something, Lord Indra!
I agree, we gods
failed to save Prahlad.
But please don't make me face
the fury of our Lord.
I'm fine being
the Lord of the heavens.
I don't want to be the departed.
Mother, perhaps you may know
how to pacify your husband!
He is my husband,
but after witnessing
his wrath and his furious avatar,
I'm fearful of approaching him.
O Grandsire, kindly suggest
a way out of this predicament.
The only one who can calm
the fury of the Lord
is the very soul for whom
that fury was awakened.
Prahlad, my dear,
kindly pacify your Lord!
Kindly abandon your wrath, O Lord.
Please look around.
Everyone is very fearful.
O Lord.
Please calm down
I offer my salutations to Lord Narsimha!
Please calm down.
Prahlada-hlada-dayine
Hiranyakasipoh Vaksah
Sila-tanka-nakhalaye
You made me sit in your lap,
and now you're caressing me
with great affection.
Have no doubt that you are
dearer to me than Brahma, Shiva,
and even Goddess Lakshmi.
O Lord!
You've incarnated
so many times in the past.
However, by incarnating
for the protection of
just this one insignificant
devotee of yours,
you've bestowed
upon me such honor,
that I cannot sufficiently
express my gratitude
even if I were to sing
your praises
for a million years in reciprocation.
I have nothing to offer you in return,
except my heart, which only has
affection for you.
The only regret is that my father,
without reason,
harbored inimical feelings against you.
Kindly forgive him!
Prahlad.
Hiranyakashyap was purified
of all his sins by my touch.
Do not worry!
I declare today,
that for all the ages to come,
you will be celebrated as one
of my most exalted devotees,
and anyone who worships you
shall undoubtedly be
a recipient of my mercy.
Hail Lord Narayana!
What's this, Lord Indra?
You seem quite pleased.
Shouldn't I be?
The hurdle has been cleared.
But let me remind you,
Jay and Vijay will be reborn twice more
before returning to the Lord.
Hail Lord Narayana!
LORD SHIVA